YWCA of the U.S.A. Records. Record Group 8. Community Associations
Sophia Smith Collection
YWCA of the U.S.A. Records. Record Group 08. Community Associations
1884-2001
Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A.
324_rg8
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
This record group documents the National Association's interactions with local YWCAs and other types of general membership groups (such as Registered Groups). Materials include minutes; reports; publications; lists; forms, policies and procedures; correspondence and mailings; constitutions and by-laws; legal files; rosters; spreadsheets; studies and surveys; training materials; and files on individual Associations dating from 1884-2002. Forms part of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records.
Forms part of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records.
NOTE: For the most part, the Microfilmed Records and the Original Format Records do not duplicate each other and both should be consulted. This description covers materials in both formats. See the Contents List for a folder-level inventory of the Original Format Records. See the Microfilmed Records Reel Lists for a detailed inventory of the microfilm. Links to the lists for both formats are provided in the Series Descriptions or Scope and Contents notes under each Record Group.
This record group documents the National Association's interactions with local YWCAs and other types of general membership groups (such as Registered Groups). Materials include minutes; reports; publications; lists; forms, policies and procedures; correspondence and mailings; constitutions and by-laws; legal files; rosters; spreadsheets; studies and surveys; training materials; and files on individual Associations dating from 1884-2002.
This Record Group is divided into four Series:
I. SERVICES TO COMMUNITY ASSOCIATIONS
II. MEMBERSHIP OF ASSOCIATIONS
III. HOLLYWOOD STUDIO CLUB
IV. COMMUNITY ASSOCIATIONS FILES
The records are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection with the following accesptions:
Portions of this collection are stored offsite. To access boxes 893-964 and 1061-1132, researchers must give two working days advance notice. Advanced notice is NOT required for other boxes or to view microfilmed records.
Access to audiovisual materials may first require production of research copies.
Additional Formats
A copy of the microfilmed records of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records is available to borrow from the William Allan Neilson Library at Smith College via Interlibrary Loan.
To request the microfilm from our library you will need to submit the following information to your library's Interlibrary Loan department:
Author: Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A. National Board
Title: Records, 1876-1970 [microform]
WorldCat Accession Number: OCLC 57415795
Notes: "Call # 689" and reel number(s) you want to borrow
Full descriptions and reel lists of the microfilm are available online.
The YWCA of the U.S.A. donated a portion of its records to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1964 and the remainder in 2002 and 2003.
Rural women--History--Sources; Sociology, rural--United States; United States--Description and travel--Sources; Women--Services for--United States; Working class women--United States--History--20th century--Sources
Record Groups
The YWCA of the USA Records are arranged as follows:
YWCA of the U.S.A. Records (main record)
RECORD GROUP 1. GENERAL AND HISTORY
RECORD GROUP 2. PREDECESSOR ORGANIZATIONS AND NATIONAL BOARD
RECORD GROUP 3. NATIONAL ADMINISTRATIVE OFFICE
RECORD GROUP 4. NATIONAL CONVENTIONS AND CONFERENCES
RECORD GROUP 5. INTERNATIONAL WORK
RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM
RECORD GROUP 7. STUDENT WORK
RECORD GROUP 8. COMMUNITY ASSOCIATIONS
RECORD GROUP 9. PHOTOGRAPHS
RECORD GROUP 10. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS
Artifacts
The Microfilmed Records
The Oversized Materials
This Record group forms part of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records
Series Descriptions
- SERIES I. SERVICES TO COMMUNITY ASSOCIATIONS
  Historical Note
  Organizational responsibility for advisory services to, and day-to-day contact with, Community Associations was especially fluid during the first twenty-five years of the YWCA of the USA. This was probably due in part to the predecessor organizations' strong insistence that the fundamental differences between City and Student Associations required very different types of national organizations for administrative support; a point of view that substantially delayed the merger of the two predecessor organizations.
  Initially, the National Association divided its staff into a Home Department (concerned with work in the U.S.) and a Foreign Department (concerned with U.S. staff working abroad). By 1909 the Association added a Department of Territorial Work with Field Secretaries in regional offices spread around the country. Part of its job was to bring together the various state and territorial committees established under the auspices of the predecessor organizations to form a coherent whole.
  A 1910 reorganization replaced the Home and Territorial Work Departments with the Department of Method (renamed Research and Method in 1919) and the Department of Field Work. The Field Work Department was to be the "direct medium of information between the National Board and the field, providing information on standards, policies, finances, and work desired and contemplated." The Department of Method, worked at "developing and perfecting YWCA methods." As the YWCA expanded into different geographic regions and set about forming Associations in smaller towns and rural districts, it assigned some staff based of the size of the community, with certain individuals specializing in City, Town, or "Extension" (later Rural) work. Other secretaries specialized in work with particular "constituent groups," such as students, industrial workers, "colored" women, teen age girls, and new immigrants. The Method and Field Work Departments both had such specialist staff. The National Association assigned Specialist Field Secretaries based on the needs of a particular region. In 1915, for instance, the West Central region had a city secretary and two student secretaries, but no industrial secretary, while the Northeastern region had a city secretary, two industrial secretaries, a county secretary, and two student secretaries.
  Method Department staff traveled the country visiting Associations and reporting on their area of expertise, but also on any other aspects of YWCA program they felt warranted comment. Field Work staff were experts in their region and communicated its needs and concerns to the national office. Both staffs contributed heavily to overall YWCA efforts, whether they were specifically assigned to the department charged with exchange of information or the department charged with development and perfection of methods.
  From its earliest staff configurations, the National Association seems to have remained unsure about whether or not it was desirable to divide responsibility for "method" and "services." The major post-World War I reorganization in 1922-23 consolidated all of the staff who worked directly with Community Associations and "constituent groups" in a newly established Field Division, taking on the "promotion and advisory service" work previously done by the Research and Method Department. Research and specialist advisory work "in the subjects in which we should be specialists" such as religious psychology, social issues, world fellowship, bible, and health moved to a new Education and Research Division. [See RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM, SERIES I. DEPARTMENT, STAFF, AND COMMITTEES.]
  Financial difficulties of the Great Depression forced a major staff reduction in 1932. Responsibility for most "constituent groups" temporarily moved to the Leadership Division [See RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM, SERIES II. TRAINING AND PERSONNEL] Services to Associations were consolidated in the new National Services Division, and the specialization of staff for City, Town, and Rural Associations was eliminated. The National Association decided it could no longer support such extensive travel by Secretaries and that they needed to develop methods for reporting on their work that were less time-consuming than the traditional narrative reports.
  The Program Planning Study of 1939 resulted in another reorganization in 1940 with the Division of Community YWCAs (later known as the "Community Division") replacing "National Services." The National Association once again combined responsibility for program subjects and constituent groups with services to Community Associations. Five years later, program development was again separated from direct services to Associations and moved to the Program Subject Department [See RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM, SERIES I. DEPARTMENT, STAFF, AND COMMITTEES.]
  By 1950 the National Association's work with constituent groups was just a fraction of what it had been at the end of World War I, and the Association concluded that it could not afford to continue so much specialist staffing, particularly for Industrial and Business and Professional work. This change reduced its constituent group-related responsibilities. However, the implementation of a system for assessing each Community Association's performance in light of a set of "basic standards" set by the National Association created a new set of tasks for the Division. The 1949 Convention approved this new concept for membership of Community Associations in the YWCA of the USA after more than a decade of study and discussion.
  Determining the Basic Standards (also known as Standards, and later, Standards of Excellence) became a part of each Convention, when plans were established for the work of the National Association in the following triennium. The Association developed, tested, and put into place a "Basic Standards" report form following the 1949 Convention. One of the elements it placed under close scrutiny was the adherence of Community Associations to the YWCA's Interracial Charter (adopted in 1946). Each triennium committees developed a set of "Basic Standards" for adoption at Convention. Once approved, they were enforced by the Committee on Membership in the National Association (MINA). Staff responsible for services to Associations assembled and maintained all of the related paperwork. Interactions between the National Association and Community Associations became increasingly about tracking each Association's financial support of the National Association, and assessing whether its administration and programs were in line with Convention actions.
  Though the YWCA had been working explicitly toward a fully integrated organization since the adoption of its Interracial Charter in 1946, nearly twenty years later much work remained to be done. In response to the growing Civil Rights movement, the YWCA of the USA initiated an Action Program for Integration and Desegregation of Community YWCAs in 1963. [See RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM, SERIES IV. CONSTITUTENT GROUPS, Subseries C. Interracial/Racial Justice] The National Board allocated special funds to help "every Community and Student Association achieve full compliance with our Interracial Charter and the Civil Rights Act of 1964." By the 1970 "One Imperative" Convention, the YWCA had developed the Action Audit for Change process. Designed to attempt to resolve institutional racism within the YWCA, the process began with every Community Association studying its own policies and programs. At the 1976 Convention, the Association established the Action Audit for Change Process as an ongoing requirement for continuing affiliation of Community and Student YWCAs with the national organization.
  In response to the rapid social change and upheaval of the late 1960s, the YWCA of the USA concluded it needed another major reorganization to serve its potential membership more effectively. The Organizational Renewal Committee developed a "Team-Matrix" plan for implementation in 1971-72, but a major budget deficit and associated staff cut precluded its full implementation and the national staff entered a period of much shifting and tweaking of organizational responsibilities.
  The idea behind the "Team-Matrix" plan was to develop a structure that would be able to respond quickly to the type of social upheaval associated with the late 1960s and early 1970s and make the most effective use of limited resources in a time of increasing demands. It was a purposefully non-hierarchical system designed to maximize communication and cooperation across the organization. Staff based in the regions were no longer so expressly associated with direct service to Associations, but were supposed to work with all of the units at headquarters. A new Organization Development Unit was put in charge of standards certification, organization of new YWCAs, and advice on operation of physical facilities (the Unit included a buildings consultant). It also included staff for Services to Urban Associations, once again acknowledging the unique characteristics of large and complex city Associations.
  The National Association struggled with the partially implemented and understaffed 'Team-Matrix' system for some years, once again consolidating services to Community Associations under a Field Services Division in 1978. Field Services included Services to Urban Associations, Organization Development, and regional staff. Field Services took responsibility for Community Association certification and the Organization Development Unit took on a more standard "O.D." role, focused on advisory service. Direct service to Community Associations in need of specific help or advice continued on a smaller scale and more often by mail or telephone than through a visit from National Staff.
  Once the National Association was more-or-less out of the business of program development, Community Associations were encouraged to share information about their new programs and methods. The National Office collected such materials for potential adaptation and dissemination to the whole Association. National staff also kept track of Associations involved in controversies and lawsuits, especially those that had the potential to make a serious negative impact on the National Association. These included pressures to merge with YMCAs, lawsuits challenging the all-female board membership policy on sex discrimination grounds (EEOC vs. Tucson YWCA), and a variety liability lawsuits.
  In the early 1980s Community Associations began agitating for improved services from the national offices. They complained of unclear lines of responsibility and a lack of accountability. They felt they weren't getting the kind of help they needed. In the resulting reorganization (1984), Organization Development was eliminated. In 1988, the National Association modified the Association Standards Review process to save costs, and replaced the visit by a National Review Team with a conference call.
  Project Redesign in 1992, a major study by KPMG Peat Marwick, Inc., evaluated the national office and its service to Community Associations. Input gathered from Associations and focus groups resulted in, among other things, a new office called Member Association Services (MAS). Technical assistance to Associations was eliminated as well as consulting on program and resource development. MAS was charged with reinvigorating state and regional councils for improved interchange of information and "rigorously enforcing adherence to the standards." Community Associations that routinely met their national support payment quotas and basic standards demanded that MINA develop a process for bringing delinquent Associations into full compliance. Whatever the intention, this tightening of enforcement resulted in worsening of relations between the national office and Community Associations as well as the loss of roughly eleven percent of Associations.
  Poor relations between the National Association and Community Associations was one major impetus for a series of strategic planning initiatives through the 1990s. A special convention in 2000, approved a major restructuring plan called "Steps to Absolute Change." [See RECORD GROUP 1. GENERAL AND HISTORY, SERIES II. REORGANIZATIONS, and RECORD GROUP 2. PREDECESSOR ORGANIZATIONS AND NATIONAL BOARD, SERIES III. NATIONAL COORDINATING BOARD]
  Administrative History
  1907 Home Department
  1909 Territorial Work Department and Home Department
  1910 Field Work Department and Method Department
  1919 Field Work Department and Research and Method Department
  1923 Field Division
  1932 National Services Division
  1940 Division of Community YWCAs
  1972 Organization Development Unit, Services to Urban Associations, and regionally-based staff
  1978 Field Services Division (includes Services to Urban Associations and Regions), and Organization Development Unit (eliminated 1984)
  1992 Member Association Services
  Scope and Content
  Records in this Series include minutes; reports; publications; lists; forms, policies and procedures; correspondence and mailings; constitutions and by-laws; legal files; rosters; spreadsheets; studies and surveys; and training materials dating from 1884-2002.
  This finding aid uses the term "Community Association" (as distinct from "Student Association") in referring to all general membership groups. The YWCA itself sometimes used "Local Association" and, in recent years, "Member Association." Also included here are materials about other general membership groups that were not full-fledged Associations, such as Registered Groups and Authorized Groups. Information on Student Associations can be found in RECORD GROUP 7. STUDENTS.
  As is true elsewhere, few records have survived for the period between 1971 and 1988.
  Department/Division records provide rich documentation of the development and growth of the National Association, its methods and program, especially in the minutes and the visitation reports up to 1931. Traveling Secretaries reported on the situation at existing Associations and in the surrounding community, as well as areas of the country where the National Association was considering establishing new Associations. Included are special studies of rural communities to determine how the YWCA, which evolved in urban settings, could serve geographically dispersed communities. In later years, similar information can be found in reports by Regional Staff. The earliest records of national staff interactions with Community Associations can be found in the minutes and reports of the Department. The National Association did not keep files on individual Community Associations until the establishment of the Field Division in 1923.
  Even though they were not always under the supervision of the department or division responsible for services to Community Associations, all of the City, Town, and Rural Communities Departments' records are filed together here in the interests of ease of access. For the years 1910-23, researchers should also consult the records of the Department of Method/Research and Method [in RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM] which officially oversaw those departments.
  Records associated with the system established in 1949, requiring Community Associations to meet 'Basic Standards' in order to maintain membership in the National Association document one of the important ways the YWCA of the USA brought about a variety of changes in Community and Student Associations, from buying in to the more radical political and social stands of the organization (including racial integration, support for the Equal Rights Amendment, etc.), to sound administrative practices (full payment of 'National Support' dues, training of Association leaders, etc.).
  Materials in this series document evolving relations between the national office and Community Associations, both good and bad. For instance, they provide extensive evidence of deteriorating relations between national and locals that lead up to the major restructuring of 1999-2001. The also provide much insight into relations with the YMCA, as many Community Associations shared facilities with the YM, and felt keenly local pressures to merge operations.
  Some unusual materials of note include: a set of Rural-Industrial Studies funded by the Ford Foundation in the mid-1920s and records of YWCA activities at the Panama-Pacific Exposition in San Francisco in 1915, (in the files of the Exposition Auxiliary Committee of the Field Work Department.)
  Microfilmed Records, 1884-1970 only
  [see Microfilmed Records Reel List]
  Most of the Minutes and Reports are also available on paper, notable exceptions being the early Field, State, and Territorial Committee files.
  Certain portions of the Subject Files materials are also available on paper, in general these include departmental publications, reports, and studies.
  Minutes and Reports
  1884-spring 1932:
  City Department
  Employment and Room Registry
  Exposition, Panama-Pacific
  Field Committees
  Field and Territorial Committees
  Field Division
  Food Service
  Rural Communities Department/Committee
  State Committees
  Territorial Committees
  Town Department
  fall 1931-1970:
  Community Division Committee
  Community Division
  National Services Division
  New Organization Committee
  Subject Files
  Department and division reports, publications, and studies can be found under:
  Advisory Correspondence Study and Procedures
  Buildings
  Dedication Services [for Community Association buildings]
  Fields and Field Work
  Food
  Housing [residences, room registry]
  Regions
  Rural
  YWCA
  Original Format Records, 1907-2001, n.d., 17 linear feet
  [see Original Format Records folder list]
  This series consists of records of the national office, staff, and committees charged with communicating with and providing services to community associations. Included are minutes, reports, correspondence, training materials, publications, etc., designed for association-wide use. This series includes some early reports on individual associations in Secretaries' visitation reports, but most of the materials about specific associations can be found in SERIES IV. COMMUNITY ASSOCIATIONS FILES of this Record Group.
  As described in the Historical Note above, staff responsible for services to Community Associations was very closely linked to the staff developing "Method" for the National Association. Even though oversight of the City, Town, and Rural Communities departments was shifted between the Field (association services) and Research and Method Departments (program and methods), the work of those departments remained consistent. For ease of access, all of the City, Town, and Rural Communities Department records are filed together in this series. Researchers should also consult the records of the Research and Method Department (which had responsibility for those departments 1910-23). [see RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM]
  The records are divided into two Subseries:
  Subseries A. Records, 1906-spring 1932
  Subseries B. Records, fall 1932-2002
  This subseries covers the period during which support staff for Community Associations specialized in services and program for larger cities, smaller towns, and rural areas. The records are arranged in sections as follows: General and History, Minutes, Publications, Reports, Special Projects, and then Studies.
  Within the first four sections (General and History, Minutes, Publications, and Reports), records of the department/division responsible for overall administration of the work (Territorial Work, Field Work, Field Division) are filed first, followed by the records of the specialized departments (City, Town, and Rural.)